It's really common to find mistakes in your code the first time you try.
第一次试行代码时 出错并不稀奇
You may forget to put a semi-colon at the end of
你可能会忘了在指令后面放一个分号
an instruction or misspell a variable name.
或者拼错了变量名
You could even do something less obvious like use the incorrect comparison operator.
甚至是犯下些不太明显的错误 比如用了错误的比较运算符
That's why IDEs like IntelliJ are super
这就是 IntelliJ 等 IDE 特别实用的原因
helpful because they can detect and point out errors like these and help you fix them.
因为它们能够检测并指出像这样的错误 帮你修正错误
But first, let's have a look at
不过我们先来看一些常见错误
some common errors and see how IntelliJ helps us resolve them.
看看 IntelliJ 是怎么帮我们解决错误的
In Java, there are essentially three types of errors programmers tend to make.
基本上 程序员在 Java 里会犯的错误有三种
The first is called a syntax error or a compile time error.
第一种叫语法错误 也叫编译错误
It's the kind of error that prevents your code from
这种错误会让代码无法进行初次编译
compiling in the first time because there is some sort of
因为它违反了Java 语言的某些语法规则
violation in the grammatical rules of the Java language like misspelling a variable name,
比如拼错变量名、
or forgetting to close a set of curly brackets,
忘记输入右花括号、
or missing a semi-colon and such.
少写了个分号等等
Luckily, syntax errors are usually pointed out immediately in IntelliJ.
好在 IntelliJ 一般会立刻指出语法错误
It would highlight a problem like missing semi-colon with this red line
错误部分会突出显示 比如少写了分号 这里就会出现红线
here and it would also highlight variables that are misspelled or unknown.
拼错或未知的变量名也会突出显示出来
The second type of errors is called a runtime error.
第二种错误叫运行错误
It's when something wrong happens while your program is running,
如果程序运行时出了岔子 那就是运行错误
like trying to access an index that is out of the bounds of an array
如访问数组范围外的索引
or dividing some number by a variable that happens to be zero at that point.
或者让某个数字除以一个变量 而该变量那个时候恰好为 0
When a runtime error occurs,
一旦出现运行错误
your program would immediately stop and it might even crash.
程序会立即停止 甚至崩溃
If you have ever experienced a program crash on you before,
如果你遇到过程序崩溃
it's very likely that an unexpected runtime error has
那很可能是发生了一个意外的运行错误
occurred that was not handled correctly by the developer who made that program.
这可能是制作程序的开发人员没有处理好造成的
We will learn a lot more about runtime errors in
在下一课中 我们会更深入地学习运行错误
the next course when we discuss exceptions and how to handle them.
届时我们将讨论意外情况及应对方法
Sometimes however, you end up with code that might seem there
不过有时候你可能发现 代码看起来没什么问题
is nothing wrong with it because the syntax is perfect,
语法没错
and it would also run fine without crashing,
运行起来也好好的 不会崩溃
but it just doesn't do what you expected to do.
可就是不按你的设想执行
This type of error is called a bug.
这种错误叫做 bug (逻辑错误)
It's when you have something incorrect in the logic of your program itself,
会出现这种错误 是因为程序本身逻辑有问题
like using the wrong comparison operation or writing your statements in the wrong order.
比如用错了比较运算符 或者语句顺序写错了
IDEs can't really detect bugs for you straight away because they
IDE 无法直接帮你指出 bug
can never know what's inside your mind or what
因为它们永远也无法知道你在想什么
you intend your program to do in the first place.
无法知道你一开始想用程序做什么
They can however, help you find bugs by pointing
不过它们能帮你发现 bug
out warning messages when it sees something suspicious,
如果有什么可疑情况 IDE 就会显示警告信息
like this condition here that would always evaluate to false.
就像这里 判断结果会一直为假
Another thing IDEs allow you to do is to step inside
IDE 还能让你在程序运行的时候
the program as it runs and watch every instruction and statement as it happens.
进入程序 观察每个指令和语句是怎么执行的
This process is called debugging.
这个过程叫调试
But before we take a look at how to use IntelliJ to debug some code,
不过在我们开始讲如何用 IntelliJ 来调试代码之前
let's see if you can tell what type of error does this code have.
我们先来看看你能否判断出这段代码的错误类型
Is it a syntax error,
是语法错误呢？
a runtime error, a bug or nothing is wrong with it.
运行错误呢？ 还是 bug？ 还是没错？